Get him out. Get him out.
>> Get a spare. Get a spare.
>> I'm going in.
>> Okay.
>> Give me light.
>> [music]
[music]
>> It is the winter of 1863.
And in Richmond's Libby Prison,
Union captives face another day of
deprivation. [music]
>> None of the castles and dungeons of
Europe have a stranger or sadder history
than this.
Many a heart has been wrung.
Many a spirit broken.
Many a noble soul has there breathed
[music] out its last sigh.
>> Get up!
Get [screaming] up!
Get up, god damn it!
>> It's the third winter of the war.
Richmond is still the capital of the
Confederacy. Both armies have sort of
gone to their winter camps and are doing
more or less nothing but trying to
survive.
>> Get up! Now!
>> The Confederate States, there was
widespread deprivation, shortages of
food, shortages of material,
no prospect of warmth or medical care
through the prison.
>> Some of the biggest concerns is going to
be lice. They'll say that's actually
their biggest enemy.
>> Richmond is growing restless.
The well-being of the prisoners from the
United States Army is the least [music]
of the Confederacy's concerns.
>> Good morning, good morning. You know the
drill.
>> They are just numbers.
>> Let's go!
>> Libby Prison was built specifically to
house Union officers, men like Captain
[music] Andrew G. Hamilton,
>> Here.
>> 12.
>> Captain Isaac M. Johnston,
and Colonel Thomas Rose.
Early in the war, both sides exchanged
prisoners regularly. But by this point,
these exchanges had virtually ended.
More than a thousand are now crammed
into this old warehouse by the James
River.
Their imprisonment isn't about
individual punishment. [music] It is
about keeping able-bodied men off the
battlefield.
>> As far as you were concerned, once taken
prisoner, you were in for the duration
of the war.
>> Apart from the daily roll calls,
captured soldiers are largely left to
their own devices.
Reading the first-hand accounts of
prisoners like Captain Isaac Johnston,
you can be lulled into feeling like they
didn't have it so bad.
But the truth is that [music] it was
horrific.
>> Throughout the Civil War era, both sides
had to create prisoner camps on the fly.
Basically on a rush job.
>> Nearly 10% of Civil War deaths occurred
in prisons like this one.
>> The way the Confederate States and the
United States treated the prisoners of
war became a major political issue
between the two sides during the war.
Well, these men are starving, they're
dying, they're freezing, they're being
treated inhumanely.
>> Care packages sent to Libby's prisoners
are treated with suspicion
and left inside an old tobacco shed,
cutting off a vital link to the outside.
>> It's just this grinding sense of
day-to-day
nothingness.
And you can imagine what that did to the
imagination
of the prisoners in Libby.
>> I know something of battle.
I am familiar with the long and weary
march,
the want of food and thirst.
I've been stretched almost lifeless,
months of sad and weary, hopeless
captivity.
Should I be a prisoner in the hands of
the foe,
lie helpless amongst the dying,
or should I escape?
>> Hello?
Hello?
Major
Hamilton.
Colonel Rose.
And you came in here with the the
Chickamauga prisoners? 77th PA.
Rebs rolled our flank.
I was captured at Jonesboro, Tennessee.
What brings you down here, Colonel?
>> It isn't uncommon for guards to plant
spies among the prisoners, so they need
to be careful.
>> So, Colonel Rose bumps into A.G.
Hamilton and realized that they needed
to pair up.
>> I estimate the river's about 45 ft that
way.
I think the sewer line is probably about
10 ft down, running along Canal Street.
You think we can do it? I think we can.
I built homes
back before the war.
So,
I think I can handle this.
Do you have some men you can trust? I
got a few men.
>> Rose and Hamilton are going to attempt
the impossible, escape from Libby
Prison.
>> 20
>> Here.
>> 21
>> Captain Hamilton's plan had been
adopted.
Solemn pledge was taken [music] to
reveal it to none others.
>> If word got out
and the prison population in general
knew about this, [music] it could
endanger the entire mission.
And this could all come tonight.
>> The prisoners sleep on the upper floors
and have access to a kitchen on the
lower floor between a makeshift hospital
and a room occupied by the prison's
rebel commanders.
On one side [music] of the cellar, the
quarters for captive African-Americans.
On the other, a storage area that has
been sealed off from the upper floors.
And in between, the notorious dungeon
where guards send prisoners when they
want to deliver a strong message.
And the entire prison is guarded by
sentries and dogs.
What Rose and Hamilton understood
immediately is that the only way out of
Libby will be to dig a tunnel out of the
East Cellar. But first, they must get
into the East Cellar undetected.
The noise coming from the nightly
gathering in the kitchen provides the
cover they need.
Hamilton, a house builder by trade,
discovers a solution.
But he only has a simple pocketknife to
execute it.
>> So, the prisoners will devise rather
ingenious stratagems of going through a
fireplace and then replacing the bricks
as they went back into the prison.
>> I got it.
>> It looked like a regular fireplace.
But it was really the secret entrance to
the cellar.
>> All right, I'm going in.
>> Okay.
>> After 15 nights of work,
Hamilton and Rose make it to the
basement
where they are met with another
surprise.
>> Rats.
Thousands of rats.
You start to feel something and hear
something scurrying around on the floor.
>> I see. So, it's maybe it Maybe this side
of the wall, yeah. River's over this
way.
>> Right.
>> The plan was to dig down and pass under
the foundation.
Then, change the direction and work
parallel with the wall to a large sewer
that passes down the Canal Street.
And from there, make our escape.
>> It's a dangerous plan.
Even if they could make it outside the
prison, they would still need to
negotiate crowded city streets, rebel
encampments, and vast swaths of nearby
swampland.
>> How we going to do it?
>> They didn't have any tools for
tunneling.
>> Oh, we're going to need a chisel
to get through all that foundation.
>> And so, they would sneak off things like
chisels,
penknives, case knives, pocket knives
that they used to dig through.
>> Spittoons for the dirt. We'll carry that
back.
>> They would grab a spittoon or a
cuspidor.
>> We need rope.
>> We're going to need a lot of rope.
>> Probably around 200 or so feet.
>> Hurry up.
>> See if it's the wall.
>> Let's see if we can get some more guys
on this.
>> 86
>> Here.
>> 88
>> Time to start digging.
>> 89
>> Here.
>> 90
>> Set chisels.
>> Ooh.
>> Welcome to Rat Hall, Mr. Rackle.
>> The tunneling team grows to include J.F.
Gallagher and a handful of others.
They are monitored closely by prison
clerk Erastus Ross.
With this many enemy soldiers held so
close to the capital, the Confederates
could not let their guard down.
>> Basically, his main job was
accountability. How many prisoners do we
have?
>> If Ross's count is off, the whole prison
would go into lockdown.
And what little autonomy the prisoners
maintained could be lost.
>> We hit water!
The tunnel's not going to work.
>> They dug too deep.
Water from a nearby canal begins to seep
in.
>> Our first plan of escape being thwarted,
no time was lost in devising another.
A second effort was made
passing through the outer wall to the
large sewer in front.
>> Private, get over here.
You hear that? Listen. [music]
>> Might just be a big rat.
>> Another attempt was to escape by the
sewer leading from the kitchen.
>> Bad news!
Bad news, it's solid oak.
It's too thick.
>> Three attempts,
three failures.
>> Come on, wake up!
>> But Rose isn't about to give up.
He devises an even more audacious plan.
>> Thank you, gentlemen. You are dismissed.
>> Ross, I need to talk to you about the
boxes.
Our men are hungry.
>> Yes.
>> May we at least retrieve the food from
them? I know Gallager can pick it up.
That's all we need.
>> Rose has been eyeing the tobacco shed on
the east side of the prison
where unopened care packages have been
hidden away.
>> My hands are tied.
>> You see how many hungry men I have here?
>> Yes, I do. But we got we've got sweet
potato
>> Erastus Ross, the prison clerk, grants
permission for one of Rose's men to
retrieve a package from the shed.
>> 45
46 47 Captain Gallager came to the
conclusion that 52 or 53 ft would bring
us to the shed.
>> 38 days after they first begin chipping
away at Libby's brickwork, the team
begins their next escape attempt.
>> What'd you find out, Gallager?
>> I walked it out. It's about 53 ft.
>> It's the longest, most daring tunnel
yet. They are digging blind. They won't
know if they've reached the shed until
they break through the surface.
>> We work in three teams of five.
We don't stop until we come out from
under that tobacco shed.
I have another 10 ft.
Should be it.
Take it down to the crew tonight.
>> Everything that happens in that hole, I
need to know about.
>> Aye.
Ah.
>> All right, everybody. DJ roll. Get up
and be in formation.
Got spittoons in the back.
In the back.
One.
Two.
Three. Here. Four. Here. Five. Here.
>> After penetrating some distance, the
task became very painful.
>> Here.
>> It was impossible to breathe the air of
the tunnel for many minutes together.
Four persons were necessary to keep the
work moving.
>> 57. Here.
>> While the tunnel continues to grow, the
digging team takes on an increasingly
risky strategy.
They dig around the clock.
>> Sergeant, we've heard of some attempted
escapes.
So, I need a named roll call.
>> Yes, sir.
>> [clears throat]
>> Gallagher.
>> Here.
>> Jeb.
>> Erickson.
>> Here.
>> Lips.
>> Hello.
Drew Casey.
>> Here.
>> Johnston.
Johnston.
>> Colonel, where is Johnston?
>> It was thought best that I should remain
down in the cellar till the tunnel was
completed.
To remain in this cold, dark, and
loathsome place was most revolting to my
feelings.
But the fear of being handcuffed and put
in the dungeon
induced [music] me to stay.
>> Ultimately, Johnston is marked down as
escaped.
There is no going back now.
In response to Johnston's missing roll
call,
security tightens inside Libby Prison.
The same is happening around Richmond.
The war [music] is not going well for
the Confederacy.
>> Richmond is still the capital of the
Confederacy. The Union Army of the
Potomac is still very much interested in
Richmond, as are the Army of Northern
Virginia in defending it.
>> Confederate armies still remain in the
field and still held the United States
armies at bay.
There were newspaper articles in
Richmond papers and in northern
newspapers that were arguing over the
condition of prisoners in Libby. The
idea was to try to rescue these people
because the newspaper reports were so
dire about their condition.
>> The prisoners aren't allowed outside,
but it is clear that messages are
getting in
and out.
>> Most people forget that there was a
large and active Union Underground.
>> Prisoners were able to remain connected
[music] to the outside world because
unsurprisingly, there were numerous
enslaved people either working nearby or
even sometimes working at the camps
themselves that would help on occasion
to provide information, maybe even
provide insight on
possible avenues to escape.
The war for freedom, the war for
patriotism was always personal for black
people in the United States.
>> While the Confederates search for the
source of the leaks on the upper floors,
they don't realize that information is
also being traded between captives in
Libby's cellar
and the servants and enslaved people
passing by the prison day to day.
>> What the prisoners discovered was a
pre-existing system
>> [music]
>> of individuals who were expert at
evading the surveillance of white
people.
>> The risk for black people, free or
enslaved, was everything.
Ultimately, their lives.
>> The night of the 7th of February came,
and it was thought that our tunnel was
long enough to reach inside of a tobacco
shed on the opposite side of the street.
We had our rations already prepared in
our haversacks, expecting to be going
out at 9:00.
>> 53
>> 53 ready
>> Okay, here.
>> Did you hear that?
>> Let me out.
>> What's he saying?
>> Run, get out.
>> Why would he call them these damn dogs
down?
What the hell are they barking at?
>> Let me out.
>> Success?
>> No, all is lost. I made a hole, a small
opening on the outside of the shed.
It was within a few feet of the sentinel
who was on guard. They'll soon be here
to arrest us.
>> Go.
>> ON GUARD.
>> GO. HURRY.
>> UP TO OUR CAR.
>> I'LL STAY HERE WITH JASPER.
>> All right.
>> [__] Got to do it.
It's cold.
>> From the windows of the third floor, the
prisoners watched the sentinels below.
In spite of the commotion, they did not
discover the hole,
and the prisoners quickly worked to
cover their tracks with a pair of pants
and some carefully placed dirt.
>> All right.
Pull me out.
>> The next night, the mining operations
were resumed.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Godspeed.
>> [laughter]
>> More air.
>> [panting]
>> I'm in.
[gasps]
[panting]
>> I made it.
We made it.
But we're going to have to wait till
tomorrow.
It's too late. We can't get everyone
out.
>> Mr. I don't know if I can do another
night.
>> No, I need you to close up the shop.
I need you to close up.
Tomorrow night.
Come on, come on. One more.
Imagine the tension.
We've done all this work. It's been 3
months.
Just one more night. What if we get
found out tonight?
>> [snorts]
>> Get up!
Get up!
>> [screaming]
>> Get up, god damn it!
>> All right, everyone. Good morning, you
know the drill. [music]
>> Let's go!
>> The 9th of February [music] was a long
day.
And long to be remembered.
Never was my anxiety so great for the
setting sun.
>> Jeb.
>> Here.
>> Gallagher.
>> Baloo.
>> Here.
>> Erickson. Here.
>> All right.
We leave two a time, 10 minutes apart,
starting at 8:00.
You bring one companion.
>> For all our effort, can we get through
one more day?
It must have been just
terrifying.
More than once during its long, dreary
hours, I feared the cup of happiness,
now so near our lips,
would be rudely dashed away.
>> It's 8:00, sir.
>> Good luck, sir.
>> Okay.
>> Keep moving, guys. Come on.
Gentlemen,
it's been a journey,
but we're not home yet.
Stay in small groups. When you get to
the surface, avoid the sentries.
Godspeed. Good luck.
Farewell.
>> There was a shade of sadness on many a
brow,
for we were about to go forth two by
two, to separate, to meet again
when?
Perhaps never.
>> [panting]
>> From 8:00 at night
to 3:00 in the morning.
109 persons thus escaped.
>> One of the challenges that the escaped
prisoners had was getting out of the
city of Richmond. Many of them had to
walk through a crowded downtown
thoroughfare to get to the outskirts of
city and move east or north toward
[music] United States Army.
>> Over the next few hours, word of the
tunnel spreads throughout Libby.
Prisoners [music] pour out of the prison
and into the frigid winter air.
Some travel through nearby wetlands to
avoid rebel soldiers.
Others tap into the Richmond underground
seeking known safe houses in and around
the city.
>> We were not observed and you may be sure
we did not linger.
Soon we were out of sight of that hated
place.
>> You've got this very tangible event
happening in the midst of the Civil War.
>> [music]
>> It's not Robert E. Lee did this or
Lincoln did that.
This is the everyday man
tunneling out of Libby, embarrassing the
Confederates, and showing them the fight
will go on
all the way to the end.
All the way to freedom.
>> Those men look like Yankees.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Mhm.